"Cognitive Stimulation, Music Therapy, and
Cryostimulation to Improve Cognitive Function"
In my book, How Not to Age,
I discuss the role
of drugs and supplements
and focus on diet
and lifestyle approaches
to the prevention and treatment
of cognitive decline,
but there are a few common
non-drug, non-supplement,
non-lifestyle approaches
to dementia treatment.
For example,
cognitive stimulation therapy,
which typically involves
group activities
and social interaction.
There have been at least 44
randomized controlled trials
of cognitive stimulation
including thousands
of participants.
ADAS-Cog, short for Alzheimer's
Disease Assessment Scale
Cognitive subscale,
is the most commonly used
measure of cognition
in clinical trials
of dementia treatment.
A clinically relevant
improvement
is often defined as a reduction
of four or more points
on the ADAS-Cog measure.
Regrettably, the attenuation
of cognitive decline
for most of the cognitive
stimulation studies
averaged only about two points.
Now you could argue,
look, any improvement
is better than nothing,
but unfortunately,
the cognitive effects
don't appear to generalize
to helping
with everyday life situations.
You can train people
to get better
at a computerized "brain game,"
but that doesn't necessarily
translate to other arenas.
Also, the marginal improvements
are temporary.
They don't seem to persist
once the intervention period
is over.
While cognitive
stimulation therapy
may have no significant
overall effect
on quality of life,
any kind of group therapy
has been shown
to improve
psychological well-being.
As social creatures,
social participation is
important for mental health
throughout the life course,
but there's
insufficient evidence
that it can improve or prevent
cognitive dysfunction.
Dementia is associated
with social isolation,
but this may be
reverse causation,
where the dementia leads
to social withdrawal,
instead of the other way around.
The same issue
comes up all the time
with those advocating
for "use-it-or-lose-it"
mental stimulation
to forestall decline.
For example, this review
in a peer-reviewed
aging journal suggested
that "if a person
solves crosswords
four times a week,
they can reduce their risk
of dementia by 47 percent."
Yes, doing
frequent crossword puzzles
is associated with lower
subsequent dementia risk,
but isn't it more likely
that those on the verge
of a dementia diagnosis
are less likely to be doing
crossword puzzles,
as a result of their declining
cognitive abilities?
Music therapy presents
a similar story
of improving well-being
without necessarily
affecting cognition.
Even in late stages
of dementia,
when verbal communication
is lost,
music can be enjoyed.
However, it does not seem
to improve brain function.
Most (five out of seven)
meta-analyses
of the 40+ interventional
clinical trials
of music therapy
for people with dementia
found no cognitive benefits.
And the few studies that did
found the effect
was short-lived,
disappearing
after one to three months.
Even though cognition
doesn't seem to be affected,
there still may be
positive effects
in terms of reducing agitation
and improving mood
and socialization.
One of the kookiest treatments
I ran across was cryotherapy,
also known as cryostimulation.
Those with mild
cognitive impairment
randomized
to short-term exposures
to extremely cold temperatures
experienced a transient boost
in general
cognitive functioning
(no longer apparent two weeks
after daily sessions ended).
Study subjects in shorts
and a T-shirt
were exposed to 58 degrees
below zero (-50 C)
for two minutes.
No, wait, that was
the placebo control group
exposed to "noncryogenic"
temperatures.
How low
did the experimental group go?
Two minutes
at more than 200 degrees
below zero (-130 C).